<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to those questions propounded by the Parliament to the Assembly of Divines, touching jus divinum in matter of church-government. Wherein is clearly proved from Scripture, that the Presbyterial government is jure devino, of divine institution, and according to the will and appointment of Jesus Christ. Licensed, and published according to order.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B526A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E340_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77729)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E340[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to those questions propounded by the Parliament to the Assembly of Divines, touching jus divinum in matter of church-government. Wherein is clearly proved from Scripture, that the Presbyterial government is jure devino, of divine institution, and according to the will and appointment of Jesus Christ. Licensed, and published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Ley, and are to be sold at his shop at Pauls Chain, neer Doctors Commons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Though this is generally attributed to Thomas Bakewell (also known as Bathwell), who matriculated at Oxford April 17, 1635, received his M.A. in 1641, and who was ejected in 1661, Thomason attributes it to a Thomas Bathwell, woolmonger.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "by Thomas Bathwell"; "by Tho: Bathwell woolmonger in [illegible]"; "June 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Westminster Assembly (1643-1652) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To thoſe QVESTIONS Propounded by the PARLIAMENT TO THE Aſſembly of Divines, Touching <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S DIVIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In matter of Church-Government.</p>
            <p>Wherein is clearly proved from Scripture, That the Presbyterial Government is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> of Divine Inſtitution, and according to the will and appointment of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 14.23.</hi>
                  </bibl> When they had Ordained them Elders in every Church, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with faſting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they believed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 5.38, 39, 43.</hi>
                  </bibl> And now I ſay unto you, refrain from thoſe men and let them alone, for if this counſel or this work be of men, it will come to naught; but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, leſt haply ye be found to fight againſt God. And to him they all agreed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed, and Publiſhed according to Order.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for WILLIAM LEY, and are are to be ſold at his ſhop at <hi>Pauls</hi> Chain, neer Doctors Commons. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159750:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159750:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to thoſe queſtions propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Parliament to the Aſſembly of Divines.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LEſt it ſhould be thought preſumption in any to undertake this work that are not of the Aſſembly, who alone were appointed for it, therefore I thought it needful to ſhew the Reader the Grounds and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that moved me to it: Firſt, it hath been long expected that the Aſſembly ſhould give in their Anſwer, and becauſe it is not, many of the Presbyterians are diſheartned. Secondly, It hath cauſed others to contemn them, ſaying, The Aſſembly have now a Bone to pick, Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It hath cauſed many to turn to the Error of</hi> Eraſtus, <hi>witneſſe the late Petition to the Parliament. Fourthly, I am confident Gods people will rejoyce, by whomſoever this work is done. For theſe cauſes I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook it, not doubting, but it will give ſatisfastion to many, and be convincing to others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, I ſhall ſpeak a few words to the Preamble, wherein it is ſaid to be reſolved by both Houſes, That perſons guilty of Scandalous offences ſhould be ſuſpended from the Lords Supper, when as Chriſt alone is the King and Maſter of the Feaſt, and hath Church-Officers as his Deputies in the Church, whom he hath appointed to ſee and judge who are worthy and who are not, and to keep the Ordinances of Chriſt from pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for if any ſhall preſume to come, not having a Wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the King will ſay to his Servants the Miniſters, <hi>Binde him hand and foot, and take him away, and caſt him into utter darkneſſe, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> Mat. 22.3, 12, 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.16, 17. <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall binde on earth, ſhall be bound in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and whatſoever ye ſhall looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven,</hi> Mat. 18.18. Iohn 20.23. But Magiſtrates are placed by Chriſt in his temporal Kingdom, and are called the Ordinance of man, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. and appointed to govern the State, and alſo by their poſitive Laws they are to be as a guide to the Church, and may be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of much good to it, ſo far as their poſitive Laws may reach about it, but not as ruling Officers in it, as ſhal more fully be ſhewn.</p>
            <p>The firſt Queſtion is, <hi>Whether the Parochial and Congregational
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159750:3"/>Elderſhips appointed by Ordinance of Parliament, or any other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational or Presbyterial Elderſhips, are</hi> Iure Divine, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Ieſus Chriſt, and whether any particular Church Government be</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and what that Government is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, If the firſt of theſe, the Parochial Congregational El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip be underſtood, the Vicar or Curate, together with the Churchwardens and Sidemen in the Pariſh, being all under the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tical Government, &amp; being neither Scripture Names nor Officers, but rather Antichriſtian Inventions; theſe cannot properly be called Elderſhips, ſeeing the Officers bear not the name of Elders, theſe have been proved by many to be rather Antichriſtian then <hi>Iure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino;</hi> and ſeeing the main pillars of Antichriſt are tumbled down, theſe bearing his name, ſhall tumble down together with him, and I hope they need no further Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The next thing conſiderable is, <hi>Whether any other Congregational or Presbyterial Elderſhips are</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> To the firſt of theſe I Anſwer Negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that there is no ſuch Church in Scripture as they call Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or Congregational Churches, and the proving of this will ſatisfie that there Congregational Elderſhips are not <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> of Divine Inſtitution, nor their Churches, but to be demoliſhed as the Prelatical, for <hi>who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean, not one,</hi> Iob 14.4.</p>
            <p>I prove the point by this Argument, If there be no Church in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture belonging peculiarly to one man, as to <hi>Peter, James,</hi> or <hi>John,</hi> and to bear his name, to be called his Church, as being peculiarly by him gathered, as they ſay, into a Church-way, as the Independent Churches are both named and gathered, then Independent Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are not of Divine Inſtitution, and if not their Churches, much leſſe their Elderſhips: But there is no ſhch Church in Scripture ſo gathered and ſo named: <hi>Ergo</hi> The Independent Church-way is of no Divine Inſtitution, much leſſe are their Elderſhips <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> or according to the will and appointment of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> part of the Propoſition I ſuppoſe all men will grant, and for the <hi>minor</hi> I ſhall prove, by taking a view of thoſe Scripture Churches, which they chiefly would have to be Independent, being of the firſt planting; firſt, that hundred and twenty names, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. ſome of them have affirmed to be an Independent Church or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, becauſe, ſay they, that 120. names was made up both of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159750:3"/>men and women, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.14. Therefore, ſay they, it was an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Church. To this I anſwer, Thoſe women there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned were not of this company, for that were before this; and thoſe men and women there ſpoken of was at prayer together, and it is very likely the cauſe of it was to ſeek the Lord for a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon this weighty buſineſſe, which was the choyce of another Apoſtle in ſtead of <hi>Judas;</hi> for in thoſe dayes it was ſaid, That <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood up in the midſt of the Diſciples and ſaid, <hi>The number of names together were about an hundred and twenty, and he that is</hi> Judas <hi>was numbred with us; but ſince he by tranſgreſſion fell, let another take his Office: wherefore of thoſe men, numbred to be an hundred and twenty together, which have accompanied us all the time that the Lord Jeſus went in and out among us, from the Baptiſm of</hi> John, <hi>unto the ſame day that he was taken up from us, muſt one be Ordained to be a witneſſe with us of his Reſurrection,</hi> Ver. 21, 22. Hence I gather, That if the hundred and twenty names was all men, as <hi>Peter</hi> here affirms, then it was not that company that was at Prayer before for a Bleſſing upon this weighty buſineſſe in the chuſing of another Apoſtle in ſtead of <hi>Judas;</hi> then this was not a ſingle Congregation, but it was the Officers were then aſſembled in a Presbytery, upon the choyce of another Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But then ſome of them ſay, <hi>That hundred and twenty names was the Mother Church, out of which all other Chriſtian Churches were to ſpring forth; therefore being the firſt it was Independent.</hi> I Anſw. If Independent Churches muſt have one as their Mother, out of which all other Independent Churches ought to ſpring forth, then I would know which of their Churches is that Mother Church; did Mr. <hi>Burtons</hi> Church deſcend out of Mr. <hi>Goodwins,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Lockers</hi> Church deſcend out of Mr. <hi>Holms</hi> his Church, or which is the Mother and which the Daughters?</p>
            <p>But it may be they will ſay, <hi>This Mother of Chriſtian Churches did firſt Baptize them, and ſo leave them, not minding whether they were truly converted or not; but then after this there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſome that gathered after them none but the godly into their Congregations out of thoſe Baptized before, and thoſe alone were the true Churches, having the Kingly Office of Chriſt, and in a Church way, and not the other;</hi> and thus our Independents do here: But then where is their proof for thoſe things? No, the contrary is the truth: for when Three thouſand was converted and became Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159750:4"/>together, and all others when they became Chriſtians were added to the Church daily, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. Then if Independents ſhould come after the Apoſtles to cull for themſelves a Church, they muſt firſt unchurch them out of that where they were placed by the Apoſtles, and ſo when they have cut them off from being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, they will prefer them to be their Members, and then promiſe them great priviledges, and Liberty of Conſcience to live as they liſt: But leſt I ſhould here make a digreſſion, I ſhall now prove that the number of names there ſpoken of, was not an Independent Congregation conſiſting of men and women, but a Presbytery of Church-Officers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If names in Scripture ſignifie Church-Officers, then that hundred and twenty names were Church-Officers, but the Saints having gotten victory over the Officers of Antichriſt, are ſaid to get victory over the number of his name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.2. And when the Officers of Antichriſt ſhall be ſlain, it is ſaid, <hi>That Seven thouſand names of men ſhall be ſlain, Rev.</hi> 11.13. Then the number of names here ſpoken of were Officers in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If there may be found ſo many Officers then in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, then that hundred and twenty names were Officers in it; but there was then eleven Apoſtles, and ſeventy Diſciples ſent out by Chriſt before this, and the reſt of that hundred and twenty names were Teachers, which had accompanied Chriſt from the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> until he was taken up, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.21. And Chriſt Ordained more to Preach then the Eleven and the Seventy; for ſaith he to another, <hi>Go thou, and Preach the Kingdom of God,</hi> Luke 9.60. Then this was was not an Independent Congregation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one particular man.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the Diſciples were then numberleſſe, then they muſt needs be more then a ſingle Congregation; but the Diſciples were then numberleſſe, for <hi>John</hi> Baptized all <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all round about <hi>Jordan, Mat.</hi> 6.5, 6. and <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples encreaſed ſo faſt, that the Prieſts and Phariſees durſt not ſay his Baptiſm was of men, for fear of the people, and <hi>Herod</hi> durſt not put him to death for fear of the people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.5.21, 23, 26. And Chriſt made more Diſciples then <hi>John,</hi> yea, they could not Baptize together their multitudes were ſo great, and the Phariſees ſaid, <hi>Perceive you not how the world is gone after him,</hi> John 3.22, 23.4.1.11.19. <hi>And people preſſed upon him to hear him Preach, and the Prieſts could not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159750:4"/>deſtroy him for the people,</hi> Luke 4.22.5, 1, 19.47, 48. Five thouſand came at one time, and Seven thouſand at another, beſides women and children; and in the open field <hi>Zacheos</hi> could not ſee Chriſt for the multitudes, but was forced to climb up into a Tree to ſee him, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.3. Then was all this but a ſingle Congregation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one man, and bearing the name of his Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If there was an Univerſal Officer to be choſen out of theſe men, and by theſe men, then it appears that they were all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers before, as the ſeventy and the eleven, and others were, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.14. &amp; 6.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.60. &amp; 10.1. Again, if it was an Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church, like one of theſe at <hi>London,</hi> then what ſhould they have to do in the choyce of an Univerſal Officer, unleſſe one Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church had power to chuſe Officers for another, which will not be granted, for that would ſoon deſtroy all their Independent Churches which muſt be alone, having nothing to do with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor they with them as a duty, only they may do ſomething if they pleaſe upon courtiſie, and they may chuſe; then this was not ſuch a one, while they choſe an Officer out of themſelves to ſerve elſwhere, and not among themſelves.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee another inſtance; Suppoſe our Independents ſhall ſay, <hi>That Church at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>that was perſecuted and ſcattered abroad was an Independent Church,</hi> Acts 8.1. Upon this ground, ſaying, <hi>They were but a ſmall number, one ſingle Congregation:</hi> for ſay they, <hi>If there had been ſuch multitudes as I ſhewed before, then how could they be perſecuted and ſcattered, and by whom were they ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted?</hi> I Anſwer, That Church at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was the Officers of the Church, and they were perſecuted and ſcattered abroad, all but the Apoſtles, and this was done by the Rulers which did not believe in Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.48. and by <hi>Saul</hi> before his converſion, he was ſent by the Prieſts to do it, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1. &amp; 9.1.</p>
            <p>And the Officers may be called a Church Repreſentative; for the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Speak to all the Congregation;</hi> and then he ſpake to the Elders of the Congregation, 12.21. And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Tell the Church,</hi> which is meant, <hi>Tell the Officers of the Church, who had both the Key of Doctrine, and the Key of Diſcipline deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them before, Mat.</hi> 16.18, 19. &amp; 18.17. So here the Church was perſecuted and ſcattered abroad, that is, their Officers; for if all the Diſciples had been ſcattered abroad, what ſhould the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles do behinde? they would not tarry if they had none left to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159750:5"/>teach, nor durſt they tarry when there was none to harbor them, and who would or who durſt harbor them if all the Chriſtians had been ſcattered and fled? but there was Diſciples ſtill that did harbor them; yea, there was then many thouſand Believers in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and this was preſently after that perſecution; as it were; with the ſame breath <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuted them, and was converted as he was going to the next Town, and came immediatly to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and then there was many thouſand Believers in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1. &amp; 9.1. compared with 21.20. Again, the Teachers were perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for they travelled as far as <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and <hi>Phenice,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> Preaching the Word of God, and they were called Prophets that came from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 11.19. &amp; 21.27. So then this Church was not an Independent Congregation, but the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Presbytery of Church-Officers, bearing the name of Church, they were perſecuted and ſcattered all abroad; but the Apoſtles, and the reaſon why the Apoſtles were not ſcattered as yet, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were more known at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by doing of many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles then other Teachers, and more convinced their Adverſaries then others, by their ſpeaking all Languages, and wiſdom that was given to them; yet it is clear by what hath been ſaid, That it was not all the people, but Church-Officers that was perſecuted, who are frequently called the Church, as hath been ſhewed: Then here is not any footing for any Independent Congregations, therefore their Elderſhip is not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> nor according to the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Then let us take another inſtance; it may be they will ſay, <hi>That Church was an Independent Church,</hi> Acts 2.47. where it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord added unto the Church daily ſuch as ſhall be ſaved:</hi> For ſay they, <hi>This was at the firſt planting of it, and then they were but few, for they were with one accord all in</hi> Solomons <hi>Porch,</hi> Acts 5.12. But I ſay, The Diſciples were numberleſſe, as I have proved already; and that Church that was in <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch, was only the Church-Officers in a Presbytery, conſulting for the good of the whole multitude of Believers; for mark the next words, The Officers being in <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch, the reſt durſt not joyn with them, they being a Presbytery, adviſing for the good of the whole Church, only the people magnified them, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 5.13. Then here we may ſee, That Church-Officers being together in a Presbytery, are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by the people; but do Independents thus, when they muſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159750:5"/>all ſit and vote with them, and in ſtead of honoring their Church-Officers in Presbyteries and Synods, they reproach them and vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and call them Antichriſtian Governors, much like <hi>Korah</hi> and his company; and it is a wonder if ſuch men ſhould dye the common death of men.</p>
            <p>But then it may be they will ſay, <hi>That Church unto which all Chriſtians muſt be added, was the inviſible Church.</hi> I Anſwer, That is a truth, but not the true meaning of this Text; and it is plain this was the Univerſal viſible Church; for when any was convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from falſe Religions to the true Religion, they were added to the Chriſtian viſible Church, as members of it; and thus the Lord added daily to the viſible Church in the ſight of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; then this Church could not be Independent, unto which all Chriſtians were added daily; neither did any Miniſter gather to himſelf a Church, but all Miniſters labored to gather Chriſtians to the multitude, but not as our Independents do to their company from among other baptized Chriſtians, and exclude all the reſt, ſaying, <hi>That they are all Antichriſtian Idolators, and without the Kingly Office of Chriſt, but his flock;</hi> Then this was not an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Church, but a Presbyterial Church, conſiſting of many Officers and much people.</p>
            <p>Again, this was not an Independent Church, for there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Univerſal Officers in it; and if yet they affirm it to be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Church, then I would know who had the peculiar charge of it, and who bare the name of it, &amp; whoſe work alone was it to gather it, as they ſay, into a Church-way? Again, if this Church did belong to one man, as to <hi>Peter, James,</hi> or <hi>John,</hi> then why muſt all Chriſtians be added to <hi>Peters</hi> Church, or <hi>Iames</hi>'s Church, or <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, or elſe be damned? Muſt Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Members be added to Mr. <hi>Burtons</hi> Church, or Mr. <hi>Lockers</hi> Members be added to Mr. <hi>Holms</hi> his Church, or be damned? Then in my judgement it were good to joyn Churches together betimes, by Presbyteries and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods before it be too late: I ſay, let us joyn all the viſible Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in the Kingdom together, and all to the Univerſal viſible Church, and as our duty ſeek the welfare of each other; and this will ſoon ſplit all Independent Churches, who are deſcended from that reprobate who ſaid, <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper.</hi> Theſe men are like the Inhabitants of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> a people that dwelt careleſſe &amp; ſecure, having no Magiſtrate in the Land to rule them or to put them to ſhame, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159750:6"/>They had no buſineſſe with any man, <hi>Iudges,</hi> 18.7. But let all faithful Chriſtians ſay with <hi>Paul, The care of all the Churches lies upon me,</hi> and rejoyce to hear the welfare of the Church in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the world, and grieve to hear that the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> are broken down; and if need require, with the Church of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> ſend relief to them in <hi>Iudea,</hi> and abhor to ſay, <hi>We are Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, we have no relation to them, nor they to us, let them ſink or ſwim, we owe them no duty, well we may counſel them, and yet we may chuſe, and they alſo may chuſe whether they will take it:</hi> Now let all judicious Chriſtians but judge, and ſpeak their conſcience, Whether Presbyterial or Independent Church Government is moſt agreeing to the Primitive Church, and be not careleſſe, but helpful one to another,; for all thoſe that are united to Chriſt, are alſo united one to another, and ſo have relation one to another, and ſtand in need of the help of each other: Then I conclude, That Congregational Presbyterial Elderſhip is not according to the Word, nor the Primitive Church, and therefore not <hi>Iure Divino.</hi> I might here ſpeak of the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Philippia,</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which were all governed by Presbyteries, and were none of them Independent, belonging to one man, bearing his name, and gathered by him, and he alone charged with it: But this may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>The next thing in the firſt Queſtion to be proved, is, <hi>Whether any particular Church Government be</hi> Jure Divino, <hi>and what is that Government?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer this by dividing the Officers in the Church from the Officers in the State, and bounding them in their place and ſtation where Chriſt hath ſet them, and to prove, That the one hath a Divine Right of Government from Chriſt in the State, and not in the Church; and the other hath a Divine Right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church, but not in the State: I prove it thus, Chriſt hath two Kingdoms, the one Temporal, and the other Spiritual: In the firſt he rules over the Kingdoms of men, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>He is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Rev.</hi> 19.16. He ſaith, <hi>By me Kings Raign, Prov.</hi> 8.15. Kings are his Deputies on Earth in this Temporal Kingdom, to Rule over the State, and outward affairs of men; and alſo in relation to the Church, they may be as a gard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, to defend it by the power of their Poſitive Laws; and alſo they may be for much good unto it, for ſaith the Lord, <hi>Cyrus is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159750:6"/>my shepheard,</hi> Iſa. 44. both to provide and care for the Church, and defend it as a Shepheard doth his flock; Kings ſhall miniſter unto it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.10. But <hi>Cyrus</hi> was not placed in the Church, he was no member of it, for he was a Heathen King, yet he had the full power of a King in relation to the Church; and a Kings being a Chriſtian addes nothing to him in point of Government in the Church, only his own benefit as a Chriſtian to enjoy the priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of it among other Chriſtians, when as <hi>Cyrus</hi> had not this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit being a Heathen: So then his power is not in the Church, but about it, he may by the Laws of the Land command obedience to the Church, and by thoſe Laws puniſh the diſobedient, yet not as an Officer in the Church.</p>
            <p>But then Chriſt hath another Kingdom, and that is Spiritual; he ſaith, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth,</hi> the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23, 24. &amp; 18.36. <hi>For this Kingdom he hath Church Officers to govern it, every member hath not the ſame Office,</hi> Rom. 12.4. <hi>The Office of a Biſhop is a good work.</hi> 1 Tim. 3.1. <hi>Theſe Chriſt hath placed in the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.28. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron and his Sons ſhall wait on the Prieſts Office,</hi> Numb. 3.10. <hi>In this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the Miniſters are his Shepheards, and all ſorts of men their flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made them over-ſeers, Acts</hi> 20.18. And they are charged to feed their flock, and to care for it, and ſaith <hi>Paul, The care of all the Churches lies upon me;</hi> he was no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent, they became Independents that ſaid, <hi>What portion have we in</hi> David? <hi>See to thine own houſe,</hi> David: <hi>to your Tents O</hi> Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. <hi>So they departed to their Tents,</hi> 1 King. 12.16. But I ſay, Church-Officers are placed by Chriſt in the Spiritual Kingdom the Church, as Kings and Magiſtrates are placed by him in the State, and not to ſtand there like cyphers to fill the place for no uſe, but to rule in it as the other do in the State, yet with this difference, Frinces and Magiſtrates have power to make thoſe Laws by which they Rule the State; for ſaith <hi>Daniel, The Lord hath given thee a Kingdom,</hi> Dan. 2.37. <hi>And they conſulted to eſtabliſh a Royal Statute,</hi> Dan. 6.7. <hi>He hath given the Earth to the Children of men,</hi> Pſal. 115.16. But the Church was never ſo given to any, no not to her Officers and Rulers, they muſt not make Laws for it, nor repeal any that are made, <hi>There is one Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy,</hi> Jam. 4.12. The Law of the Church is unalterable, like that of the <hi>Medes</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:159750:7"/>and <hi>Perſians, Not one tittle of the Law ſhall fail,</hi> Mat. 5. <hi>Their King is eternal, and with them to the end of the world,</hi> Mat. 28.20. <hi>And of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end,</hi> Luke 1.33. But Kings and Magiſtrate, are placed by Chriſt in the Temporal Kingdom, there indeed they rule with Power and Authority, but they may not rule ſo in the other Kingdom, the Church of Chriſt, for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, If, Kings and Magiſtrates ſhould rule in the Church, as Emperors rule the State, this were to dethrone Chriſt, who alone is placed and ſet by the Lord his King upon the holy hill of <hi>Sion, Pſal.</hi> 2.6. And what affront is done to his Officers in the Church, he takes as done to himſelf; and no man ought to uſurp the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Church-Officers, any more then Church Officers ought to uſurp the Office of Magiſtrates, for both muſt keep their place where Chriſt hath ſet them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If Magiſtrates ſhould rule in the Church, as Officers in it, this would confound the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt, with the Kingdoms of men, when as Chriſt hath plainly divided them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.36. both by precept and example, commanding and alſo <hi>giving to God the things of God, and to Ceſar the things of Ceſar,</hi> Mat. 22.21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If State-Officers and Church-Officers were the ſame, and he that hath one hath both, then it would follow, That Chriſt and his Apoſtles both did and taught rebellion in all places where they came, when they ſet up Elders or Church Officers in every Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. <hi>And when Chriſt expounded the Law in his own name, Mat.</hi> 5. But this were Blaſphemy to affirm; for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of Chriſt is Spiritual, and allowed by Princes and Magiſtrates where ever they came, for they know that it did not intrench upon their Authority.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Church Officers have Gods Law for their rule, but Magiſtrates have the Laws of the Common-wealth for their rule; then they muſt keep their places, the one to rule in the Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterially, becauſe Chriſt their King is with them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. and the other in the State with Majeſty and Authority, becauſe the God of Heaven hath given them a Kingdom, power and glory, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Many Kings and Magiſtrates are not ſo much as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, but rather Enemies of it: and if they were Members, yet they were unworthy of that place, to rule in the Church, unleſſe they were well skill'd in Divinity to rule in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly; but this were Treaſon to affirm.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:159750:7"/>
            <p>Sixthly, If Kings and Magiſtrates had power in the Church by vertue of their place, then they might obtain this power by War, or by Uſurpation, or Purchaſe, or by Inheritance, and ſo women would rule in the Church, that are not permitted to ſpeak in it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. and children ſhould rule in the Church, when as a Biſhop muſt not be a Novice or a yong Scholler, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and the meaneſt Officer in the Church muſt firſt be proved, before they be admitted, Verſ. 6.10.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If Magiſtrates power were in the Church, they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have this power from being a Magiſtrate, or from being a Chriſtian; but if from being a Magiſtrate, then all Magiſtrates and Princes muſt have the like power to rule the Church, as well as they, or elſe they are not perfect Magiſtrates or Princes; and if they ſhould have power to rule in the Church, becauſe they are Chriſtians, then all other Chriſtians may rule in the Church as well as they, for all are one in <hi>Chriſt, Gal,</hi> 3.28. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>Then Church Officers, together with their Names and Offices, are not to be created nor appointed by the Parliament as their creatures, when as themſelves are not Church Officers; and if they were, yet they have no power to give. Titles, Names, Offices or Officers in the Church, for that is peculiar to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the King of his Church,</hi> Eph. 4.11. and from him all Church Officers have both their Names and Offices immediatly, and therefore Church-Officers are <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> and that for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, If Church-Officers are placed by Chriſt in the Church, then they are not of Humane Inſtitution, but of Divine Right; but <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſet ſome in the Church Apoſtles, Prophets, Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, helps or Deacons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. then they being ſo placed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Church, they are <hi>Iure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If it was both the Apoſtles command, and alſo their practiſe to ſet up Elders in every Church, then Elders are <hi>Iure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> of Divine Inſtitution; but <hi>Paul</hi> left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Creet,</hi> to ſet in order things that were wanting, and to Ordain Elders in every city as he had appointed, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. And theſe were not Magiſtrates, for ſuch were before in every city; but theſe were then wanting which <hi>Paul</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> appointed <hi>Titus</hi> to Ordain in every city; neither were the Miniſters to Ordain and ſet up Magiſtrates, and yet by their own practiſe they did Ordain Elders in every Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. then they are not of Humane, but of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:159750:8"/>
            <p>Thirdly, If both the key of Doctrine, and of Diſelpline were given to Church Officers by Ieſus Chriſt, then they alone have a Divine Right to uſe them; but the keys were not given to the whole Church, but to the Officers, for ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Peter, To this will I give the Keys,</hi> Mat. 16.19. <hi>And whatſoever the Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhall binde on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven; and what they looſe on Earth ſhall be looſed in Heaven, Chap.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18. <hi>And what ſins ye remit ſhall be remitted, and what ſins ye retain ſhall be retained,</hi> Iohn 20.23. Then they alone have a Divine Right to uſe them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If Chriſt commanded the Church to obey thoſe that have the rule over them, in the Church, and not in the State, then ſuch only are to rule in the Church: But ſaith <hi>Paul, Obey them who alſo have ſpoken unto you the Word of God, &amp; they that watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account;</hi> neither muſt all the Saints rule in the Church, for ſaith <hi>Paul, Salute them that have the rule over you, and all the Saints, Heb.</hi> 13.17, 24. then they are of Divine Inſtitution, and muſt rule in the Church, and take care for it as for their own houſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4 5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If the Chriſtian Church had thoſe Officers placed in it by Chriſt and his Apoſtles before they had any Magiſtrates, or any humane Laws in it, then they are of Divine Inſtitution, and no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ought to take that from them which Chriſt gave them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had any Magiſtrates in the Chriſtian Church; but they choſe and ordained Elders in every Church before they had any Magiſtrates, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. then they are not of Humane, but of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, This Diſcipline was in the hand of Church-Officers, if they onely were blamed if it was neglected: But the Lord ſaid to Church-Officers, <hi>I have ſomething againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Iezebel to teach, and to ſeduce my ſervants, and others were blamed, becauſe there was ſome among them that held the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Balaam,</hi> Rev. 2.14, 20. Then here it is plain that both the Key of Doctrine, and the Key of Diſcipline are in the hand of Church-Officers by Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If this Diſcipline was ever in the hand of Church-Officers, it ought to be ſo ſtill: But, ſaith <hi>Paul, I have delivered Hymeneus and Alexander to Satan, that they may learn not to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.20. and concerning the Inceſtuous perſon he ſaith,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159750:8"/>
               <hi>I have judged already, and do not ye judge thoſe that are within, caſt out therefore that wicked perſon,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.3, 12, 13. And if any ſay that all muſt judge from this Text: I Anſwer, All are to refer it to the Presbytery, but ſufficient is that puniſhment that was inflicted by many, not by all, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. Chriſt gave his life a ranſome for many, not for all, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. Again, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> a Church-Officer, <hi>He that troubleth you ſhall bear his judgement, whoever he be,</hi> Gal. 5.10 Then this may ſuffice to anſwer the firſt Queſtion, That the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Elderſhips are <hi>Iure Divine:</hi> yet if any be not fully ſatisfied, I ſhal yet make it more clearly appear by anſwering a queſtion, thus,</p>
            <p>Suppoſe there ſhould be any diſturbance in the Church aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the publike Worſhip of God, by ſome Drunkard or mad man, or any Heretick, either by Sporting, or by Railing, or Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or any abominable action: where lyes the power to ſuppreſſe it? Is it in the Magiſtrates, or in Church-Officers? I anſwer, It is in the hand or power of Church-Officers, firſt, becauſe they were charged to keep the door, that there may be no ſuch occaſion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance in the midſt of Divine Worſhip, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.12, 19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this power was in the hand of Church-Officers; for when <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the King would needs burn Incenſe, the valiant Prieſts bade him go out of the Sanctuary, and cut him off from the houſe of the Lord: Neither was this becauſe he was leaprous, but becauſe he offered Incenſe; and as they were thruſting him out, his leproſie appeared, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 26.17, 18, 21. and when they were weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publikely for the abominable whoredom with the daughters of <hi>Moab,</hi> there was ſuch an action committed in the aſſembly in the ſight of <hi>Moſes,</hi> mark that, yet <hi>Phinehas</hi> the Prieſt executed juſtice, and the wrath of the Lord was pacified, <hi>Num.</hi> 25. And when <hi>Elies</hi> Sons lay with the women when they aſſembled at the Tabernacle door, and he did not reſtrain them, the Lord ſlew all his whole houſe, and that ſin could never be purged with Sacrifice, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.22. and 3.13, 14. Then if the Lord was ſo well pleaſed with <hi>Phine as</hi> the Prieſt for his juſtice, and ſo offended with <hi>Eli</hi> the Prieſt for neglecting of it, when committed in the congregation, then the power to ſuppreſſe ſuch abominations committed in the aſſembly, is in the hand of Church-Officers. Again, when there was buying and ſelling in the Church, Chriſt drave them out, becauſe the Lord ſaid, <hi>My houſe ſhall be called the houſe of Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, when Iſrael committed Idolatry not onely in private,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159750:9"/>but in the Aſſembly, the Lord cauſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to cull out thoſe that were on his ſide, and ſheath their Swords in thoſe Idolaters, and the Levites came forth and did ſo, and the Lord for that very action put them into the Miniſtry: Then it is plain, the Lord would have the Church Diſcipline in the hand of Church-Officers, they muſt keep the Ordinances of Chriſt from pollution: and thoſe that do not rule well their own houſe, are not fit to take care for the Church of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. as if he ſhould ſay, That man that is negligent to uſe Family-Diſcipline, is not fit to be made a Church-Officer, leſt he neglect the Church Diſcipline; yet all this hinders not, but that Magiſtrates may puniſh all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the State, if their Poſitive Laws will reach it, but not elſe; yet I ſay, Church-Officers are charged to keep the Ordinances of Chriſt from pollution, and for that end they are placed by him in the Church by Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>The Parliaments ſecond Queſtion is, <hi>Whether all the Members of the ſaid Elderſhips, as Members thereof, or which of them are</hi> Jure Divino, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, as before, The Independent Elderſhips are not of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, becauſe their Congregations are not; but all the Members of every Presbytery or Elderſhip, they have this Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline committed unto them, for what was ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> was ſaid to all the Miniſtery, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23. Then I conclude that all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the Presbytery, ſo called by <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>The ſtate of Elders, Acts</hi> 22.5. And it is called, <hi>The Aſſembly of the Elders,</hi> Pſa. 107.32. Therefore they are all <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> by the will and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome Independent will ask, <hi>Why their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belonging to one man is not of Divine Inſtitution, as well as a Presbyterial Congregation belonging to one man?</hi> I anſwer, There is this difference: The Presbyterial Congregation is a part of the Univerſal viſible Church, as a branch of it, which is deſcended from the firſt Chriſtian Church, although it paſſed under Antichriſt, and ſo was defiled; yet ſtill God had his Church amongſt Papiſts, and at the length brought it out of <hi>Babylon</hi> by <hi>Luther</hi> and others; and our Miniſters are deſcended from the Apoſtles, whom Chriſt Ordained to Preach, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.14. And they were ſent into all Nations to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men to the Chriſtian Faith, and they alſo Ordained Elders in every Church, in every City or Town, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. And after them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159750:9"/>they left others in their place to do it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. And thus Church-Officers were Ordained by them of their own calling ſucceſſively ever ſince, although they paſſed under Antichriſt till <hi>Luther</hi> renounced them, and by him and others was brought out what they had from Chriſt, and left what was of their own Invention, and he cauſed them to proteſt againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo they were firſt called Proteſtants: And then in <hi>Calvins</hi> time they made a Covenant to ſet up the true Diſcipline of Ieſus Chriſt; and we in this Kingdom have done the like, both by a Proteſtation againſt Popery, and a Covenant to ſet up the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of Ieſus Chriſt; therefore our Congregations are of Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but Independent Congregations original deſcent is but from themſelves, and that within this few yeers to our knowledge Tradeſmen have gathered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches; but who ſent thoſe Tradeſmen to Preach? and how can they Preach unleſſe they be ſent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. By what Authority do they Preach, and who gave them that Authority? <hi>Chriſt taught as one having Authority,</hi> Mat. 21.23, 24. &amp; 7.29. Then Independent Congregations are not of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>But they will ſay, <hi>That our Pariſhes remain ſtill as they did under Antichriſt.</hi> I anſwer, Pariſhes were divided for better convenience of Publike Worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Antichriſt was in being, when the Apoſtles gave order to ſet up Elders in every city, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and they were bounded within a Sabboth dayes Iourney for Publike Worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12. And now Prelats caſt out, our Pariſhes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in that firſt Inſtitution, for thoſe Elders were bounded to that town or city where they were ſet up; but Independent Congregations are boundleſſe, their Members thirty or fourty miles aſunder, that they cannot congregate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; therefore they are not of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>The Parliaments third queſtion is, <hi>Whether the Supreme Aſſemblies or Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips,</hi> viz. <hi>The Claſſical, Provincial and National; Whether all, or any of them, and which of them are</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Their fourth queſtion is, <hi>Whether Appeals from Congregational Elderſhips to the Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical, Provincial and National Aſſemblies, or to any of them, and to which of them are</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt; And are their Powers upon ſuch Appeals</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Their fifth queſtion is, <hi>Whether Oecumenical Aſſemblies are</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Divino; <hi>And whether there be Appeals from any of the former Aſſemblies to the ſaid Occumenical</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the ſubſtance contained in theſe three queſtions is this; Firſt, Whether Claſſical, Provincial, National or Oecumenical Elderſhips or Aſſemblies be <hi>Jure Divino?</hi> Secondly, Whether Appeals from Congregational Elderſhips to Claſſical, Provincial and National Aſſemblies are <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> or which of them, or any of them to Oecumenical be <hi>Iure Divino;</hi> and are their Powers upon ſuch Appeals <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> by the will and appointment of Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe I have ſufficiently proved, That the Aſſembly of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Presbytery are Scripture Names, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.32. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. And theſe I have ſhewed, that they are frequently called the Church becauſe they do repreſent it: And now I ſhall prove, That Appeals from the leſſer Elderſhips to the greater, is according to the Word of God, and that their power is of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, to ſuppreſſe Error and prophaneneſſe, in caſe the Magiſtrate will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159750:10"/>not by his Poſitive Laws, or to caſt them out of the Church, rather then the Ordinances of Chriſt ſhould be polluted: I prove it thus, If there was Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Church Officers in the Chriſtian Church, who met together for this end, then they ought to do ſo ſtill; and if there was Appeals from the leſſer of thoſe Aſſemblies to the greater in the Primitive Church, it ought to be ſo ſtill; and if thoſe Aſſemblies had power to make Decrees, and paſſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and to binde ſeveral Churches to obey them, it ought to be ſo ſtill, for we and all Chriſtians pretend to be under the ſame Diſcipline of Chriſt as they were; but ſome in the Chriſtian Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> would ſtill obſerve <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Cermeonies, and they had no ſmall Diſputation about it, and yet could not ſuppreſſe it being parties; therefore they determined to ſend <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not to a ſingle Congregation for advice and councel, but to the Aſſembly of Apoſtles and Elders who came together to conſider of that matter, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1, 2, 6. And I think there was but two Apoſtles there, and ſo there was at <hi>Antioch,</hi> only they were parties, and ſo they were not at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> But ſome will ſay, <hi>What if they will not come to the Aſſembly or Elderſhip, how then can they ſuppreſſe Error or Prophaneneſſe?</hi> I anſwer, The Magiſtrate muſt by his Poſitive Laws command obedience to the Church; and in caſe they will not obey the Magiſtrate, he muſt puniſh them by his Poſitive Laws; but in caſe the Magiſtrate will not do it, then the Church-Officers have power to caſt them out, to keep the Ordinances of Chriſt from pollution: So then if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate do his part, and Aſſemblies of Church-Officers alſo do theirs, this will ſweetly ſettle peace among the Churches; and this is according to the Word of Chriſt, and therefore of Divine Inſtitution: And for the Names of thoſe Aſſemblies, let them be called by any names of diſtinction, and it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth; I hope we ſhall not contend about Names, but rather labor for peace and a ſweet enjoyment of all the mercies of God both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Queſtion is this, <hi>Whether by the Word of God, the power of Judging and declaring what are ſuch Notorious and Scandalous Offences, for which perſons guilty thereof are to be kept from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting before them, trying and actual ſuſpending from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ſuch Offenders accordingly, is either in the Congregational Elderſhip in Presbytery, or in any other Elderſhip, Congregation or Perſons? And whether ſuch powers are in them only, or any of them, and in which of them</hi> Iure Divino, <hi>and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer to the firſt part of this queſtion, That Church Officers by the perfect rule of Gods Word, have power to judge and declare what ſins are ſcandalous, for which thoſe that are guilty are to be puniſhed by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; but in caſe he will not do his duty, then for the ſame, Church-Officers have power to caſt them out of the Church, to keep the Ordinances of Chriſt from pollution; ſome of them <hi>Paul</hi> mentions before his Inſtitution of the Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. ſuch as theſe, as, Drunkenneſſe, Hereſie, Diviſions, and Contentions, and men wearing long hair, and women with the hair out or uncovered, all theſe muſt be Reformed, for theſe are Scandalous; and then there are inward ſins, as, Ignorance, not diſcerning the Lords body; but the communicants muſt examine themſelves of this, and ſo let them Eat, they are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159750:10"/>not to be caſt out for Ignorance, all did eat the Paſſeover, and all them in the Primitive Church did receive the Supper, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. &amp; 20.7. Neither do I finde any ſuch thing in Scripture, as ſuſpenſion from one Ordinance when they freely enjoy all the reſt: Neither do I finde ſuch trying and conventing, as in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Courts, they are not to caſt out for private ſins; when a private treſpaſſe was brought to the Church Officers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. they could not caſt him out, but ſaid to the Plaintiff, <hi>Let him be to thee as a Heathen or a Publican,</hi> that is, <hi>Do thou keep no company with him:</hi> Church-Officers muſt ſay as the Lord did, <hi>I have not found it by ſecret ſearch,</hi> Ier, 2.34. But when they declare their ſin, as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and hide it not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.9. As <hi>Elies</hi> Sons did, to make the offerings of the Lord to be abhor'd, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.17. And when <hi>Phineas</hi> the Prieſt ſlew <hi>Zimry</hi> and <hi>Cozby, Numb.</hi> 25. And when <hi>Uzza</hi> was caſt out of the Houſe of the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.21, And Chriſt whipt them out of the Temple; all theſe need no witneſſe, but were caſt out, all but <hi>Elies</hi> Sons, and becauſe <hi>Ely</hi> the Prieſt did not do it to his Sons, the Lord utterly cut off <hi>Elies</hi> houſe.</p>
            <p>The next thing in this queſtion is, <hi>In whoſe hand is this Power?</hi> To this I have anſwered, In the hand of the Presbytery or Church Officers: If the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be Scandalous to many Congregations, the greater Presbytery is to caſt him out; but if in ſome Country town there be but one Church, and the parties haunt be no further, I ſuppoſe they may caſt him out of their Church, and not to ſuffer him to abuſe the Ordinances of Chriſt; but no other hath this power, neither Independent Congregations nor Prelats; for Presbyterial Church-Officers are only <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and by the will and appointment of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh queſtion is, <hi>Whether there be any certain and particular Rules expreſſed in the Word of God, to direct the Elderſhips or Presbyteries, Congregations or Perſons, or any of them, in the Exerciſe and Execution of the Powers aforeſaid, and what are thoſe Rules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the Name of all Church-Officers, <hi>We will not leaſt of things without our meaſure, but according to the meaſure of the rule which God hath diſtributed to us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. Then here all may ſee that they have a Rule, and he ſaith, <hi>Let us walk by the ſame rule,</hi> Phil. 3.16. <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule, Peace be unto them,</hi> Gal. 6.16. Now by this Rule <hi>Paul</hi> judged, though abſent, that the Inceſtuous perſon ſhould be caſt out, and by the ſame Rule the Church-Officers of <hi>Corinth</hi> caſt him out, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3.12, 13. And if any ſhall ſay he ſpake to all in the Church: I anſwer, It was to give their conſent, but that puniſhment was to be inflicted by many, but not by all; ſee the ſame man caſt out, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. And he caſt out <hi>Hymeueus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> for blaſphemy; yet I ſuppoſe there was others with him, though he paſſed the ſentence, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. And ſaith <hi>Paul, He that troubleth you with the leven of Hereſie, ſhall hear his judgement whoever he be, and I have confidence in you through the Lord Jeſus, that you will be none otherwiſe minded, but give your conſent: I would they were cut off that trouble you,</hi> Gal. 5.9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>The eighth queſtion is this, <hi>Is there any thing contained in the Word of God, that the Supreme Magiſtracy in a Chriſtian State may not judge and determine what are the aforeſaid Notorious and Scandalous Offences, and the manner of Suspenſion for the ſame; and in what particulare concerning the Preniſes is the ſaid Supreme Magiſtracy by the Word of God, excluded?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:159750:11"/>
            <p>I anſwer, The Supreme Magiſtracy is to judge and determine of the ſame ſins by the Poſitive Laws of the Land, and puniſh the Offenders according to thoſe Laws, in the Temporal Kingdom of Chriſt; but he may not judge and determine of them in the Church, about caſting out by Excommunication, that is, the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt, and his Church-Officers are Spiritual Officers, and therein State Officers are excluded, as I ſhewed before.</p>
            <p>The ninth queſtion is, <hi>Whether the proviſion of Commiſſioners to judge of Scandals not enumerated, as they are Authorized by the Ordinance of Parliament, be contrary to that way of Government which Chriſt hath appointed in his Church, and wherein they are ſo contrary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That Chriſt alone is to give both Offices and Officers, and alſo their names; but Chriſt never gave any ſuch for his Church as Commiſſioners, neither muſt Parliaments create any Names, or Offices or Officers, as their creatures, to be ſet up, and appointed their work in the Church, it is a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to Chriſt the King of the Church to do it: It is obſervable, <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt received gifts for men,</hi> Pſal. 68.18. And then <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He gave gifts to men,</hi> Eph. 4.11. So then Chriſt as Mediator received thoſe gifts of his Father, and then gave them to his Church; but there is but one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. Then there was none but he that received thoſe gifts for the Church; and therefore no other can give them. Again, the Authority of the Parliament will not bear them out, when Chriſt will diſclaim them as Vſurpers, whom he never palced in the Church: And what profit or bleſſing to the Church can be expected from thoſe that Chriſt never ſent nor placed in the Church. Again, the Parliament that ſent them, are themſelves placed by Chriſt in his Temporal Kingdom, the State or Common-wealth, to govern that, and place Officers in it; but they may not Ordain Church-Officers, that muſt be done by Church-Officers, and that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively from Chriſt, who firſt Ordained the Twelve, and then the Seventy; and then the Twelve being ſent to all Nations after his death, they did Ordain Elders in every Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. And then they left others to Ordain El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſucceſſively: Saith <hi>Paul, I left thee to Ordain Elders in every Church,</hi> Tit. 1.5. And ſo it hath been by them ſucceſſively to this day: Then I conclude, That for State-Officers either to Ordain Elders, which ought to be in the Church, or to create new Officers in the Church, is contrary to that way of Government which Chriſt hath appointed in his Church, and I have ſhewed wherein it is ſo contrary.</p>
            <p>The tenth and laſt is onely a perſwaſion that thoſe of the Aſſembly would ſet down their Names, together with their Votes, whether Affirmative or Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to thoſe former particulars, and the clear Texts of Scripture on which their Opinions are grounded: Now none but the laſt concerns me, which I have done; and if the Lord be pleaſed to ſet it home to the ſoul, it may be conviction and ſatisfaction to it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
